Guide to the Howard E. Buswell papers and photographs 1822-1965
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
- Audio Collection, 1956-1964; Series XIV
  - Philip Clark and John Nichols, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #2)
    Cassette Tape #1: Philip Clark speaks of "Dirty" Dan Harris. His physical description, and character. The history of his properties in Fairhaven. Covers a period to 1891, when Dan Harris left. Tells the legend of what happened to Dan Harris after he left the Bellingham area. Dan Harris' exact location in Fairhaven on Dead Man's Point. Dan Harris known to do business in Marietta. He would come over by boat. Speaks of Dan Harris's supposed occupation as a smuggler. Dan Harris as a renowned womanizer. Speaks of the kind of transportation used around the turn of the century. Dan Harris a single man, but was known to have had a regular woman, who in the end "took him to the cleaners." Speaks to his uncle Bob Moran. Dan Harris as an educated, "cultured" (here meaning well read) man. Speaks to the lay of Fairhaven during Dan Harris's time (trees, mills, docks). Indian burial ground on Dead Man's Point where Dan Harris built his house/hotel. He still let people bring bodies in on boats to be buried. Dan Harris being able to speak Chinook Jargon. John Nichols came to Bellingham on June 1888. Lived in Marietta with Michael Clark. Helped put in the first telephone wire that extended to New Whatcom. Speaks to his recollections of Dan Harris. Speaks of character, appearance and land holdings. Attests to his wealth.
    Cassette Tape #2: John Nichols speaks of the lay of Fairhaven at the time of his arrival. Speaks to mills, saw mill in Happy Valley district. Buswell concludes and reflects on the two previous interviews: November 21, 1957. He made recordings two years previous to this conclusion. Gives weather report.
  - Charley Kahana, 1956 June 18 (Reel-to-reel Reel #3)
    Cassette Tape #1: Charley Kahana plays many selected tunes on his violin for Howard Buswell. Speaks between songs about his opportunities playing in public. Called the "Blind fiddler" or the "Indian fiddler" by those who knew him and his musical abilities.
  - Charley Kahana, 1956 April 11 (Reel-to-reel Reel #4)
    Cassette Tape #1: Lummi Village on the mouth of the Nooksack River. Charley is 91. In 1878 and 1879 Charley played for Colonel May, at the Colonel's dance. The murder of George Phillips. George Phillips, married Billy Lears's mother, but danced with Charley's half-sister and this caused problems. George was shot over the feud between his wife's family and him. George Phillip's wife left the area after that, but was detained in Port Townsend and bore a son, Tommy Phillips, while in jail. After she got out she picked hops along with many Lummis. Charley speaks of Mason Fitzhugh, who married Johnny Pierson's sister. Charley's first musical experience was on San Juan Island, where, as a young boy, he saw some fiddlers at a dance at the Champeau place. He made his first fiddle out of split cedar with a horse tail bow. His father use to sell shingles/shakes at Victoria, and worked on the farms in the islands (San Juan). His mother was a widow (after John Bull died) when she married his father. His father came to the area on a ship, a whaling ship. Charley tells of his father's travels before coming to Lummi. Howard Buswell reads a letter written to Charley Kahana from John Bull's relatives (Charley's sisters Margaret and Jane) living in California. Transcript available. Transcript available.
  - Charley Kahana, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #5)
    Cassette Tape #1: Charley Kahana Fiddling. Charley sings "Digging clams down in Bellingham Bay." About half way through the song the tape is irreparably damaged, and about one or two minutes have been lost. It picks up again with Charley fiddling. Charley plays a piece called "Taking Nelly home" which he use to play at the Coupeville picnic. Sings "Pop goes the weasel" in Chinook Jargon.
    Cassette Tape #2: Charley Kahana continues playing his violin and singing. An interview with Charley Kahana and John Nichols follows. Charley speaks of his land, and proving up his grandson as Indian of Samish, Swinomish ancestry in Everett. Charley speaks to living on Orcas Island as a young man. He went to school on San Juan Island, with his brother Joe Bull. Speaks to his ties to Lummi through his mother. Charley tells how scooners were used to haul lumber. Charley tells of working as a scooner pilot. Charley enumerates all the people he remembers knowing on Orcas Island. Charley speaks to knowing Captain Basford. Charley and John recall the steamboat workers. Speaks to knowing a MacDonald who owned a store on the reservation around 1872. Charley then speaks to canoeing from the islands to the Lummi mainland (reservation). Charley speaks to Joe Hemerly, his sister's husband, and Joe's homestead up the Nooksack. Transcript available.
    Cassette Tape #3: John Nichols speaks to the people he knew in the late 1800s on Orcas Island. Break in the tape occurs where reel is damaged. Charley speaks to Burt Squi-qui, and Billy Clark of Orcas Island. Charley speaks to driving horses in the woods for the lumber companies. Charley speaks to his work as a scooner driver, his wages and daily life, pastimes. John and Charley recall the Wynns in Marietta and how (if) they tie into Lummi. John and Charley speak to Joe Bull's daughters. Both speak to the Buechets. Transcript available.
    Cassette Tape #4: Howard and Charley speak to Charley's fiddle playing at various places and contests like the Puyallup Fair in 1925. John and Charley speak to General Miles, a steamboat that came from Port Townsend.
  - Mrs. Victor Roth, Mrs. W. H. Abbott, and Mrs. Henry Jukes, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #6)
    Cassette Tape #1: Howard introduces Mrs. Roth and the Roth House, which is situated between Ferndale and Whatcom. Howard recalls Mrs. Roth's mother-in-law (Lottie Roth). Howard and Mrs. Roth speak of peonies. Mrs. Roth speaks of when Captain Roeder lived in the Roth House. Mrs. Roth speaks of the elm tree in front of the Roth House planted by Captain Roeder. Howard asks about wedding receptions that were held at the Roth House. Mrs. Roth recalls these receptions, particularly the reception of Mrs. Abbott, daughter of Mrs. Roth's mother-in-law. Mrs. Roth and Howard recall the lay and furnishings of the Roth House. Mrs. Roth talks about the egg hunt that her mother-in-law use to have at the Roth House. Mrs. Roth continues to talk about the Roth mansion. The lumber that was used for the house was all cut at the Roeder mill in Nooksack. Mrs. Roth talks about selling the house. Mrs. Roth talks of having balls on the third floor of the Roth house. Mrs. Roth speaks about the lumber that was cut for the Roth house off of Roeder's homestead in Nooksack. Mrs. Roth talks about Captain Roeder's first home.
    Cassette Tape #2: Howard begins a different interview with Mrs. Abbott (daughter of Lottie Roth), Mrs. Roth's sister-in-law. She lived in the Roth house as a girl. Howard notes that he lost half of the interview, thus it picks up in progress. Mrs. Abbott speaks of Collier, who built a house on Eldridge Ave. Mrs. Abbott speaks about Fred Drake. Mrs. Abbott speaks of her friendship with Mrs. Jukes (Eldridge's daughter), their rivalry and Mrs. Jukes' house. Mrs. Abbott shows Howard her furniture that was Mrs. Roeder's, and they discuss certain pieces. Howard speaks of the Glimpse, Captain Roeder's personal ship. Mrs. Roth speaks about Mrs. Edson and her book about local history. Mrs. Abbott speaks about her grandfather, Captain Roeder, and his travels, routes, to the Whatcom area through California from Ohio. Mrs. Abbott talks about how her mother and father got married. Her mother was from Olympia. Mrs. Abbott speaks about watching her grandfather die in the Roth house. Howard tells about Captain Roeder's journals, and relays a few stories from what he has read. One story has to do with Cap. Roeder going to collect shingle bolts on the Lummi reservation. Mrs. Abbott speaks of her mother finishing the Roth house after Cap. Roeder's death. [Break in tape where reel was changed] Mrs. Abbott talks about her brother, Mrs. Roth's husband. Mrs. Abbott talks about the sale of the Roth house.
    Cassette Tape #3: Mrs. Abbott talks about the property surrounding the Roth House. [Break in tape where reel was turned] Mrs. Abbott continues talking about the outlaying features of the property, i.e. the cemetery, barn, carriage house. Mrs. Abbott speaks about how cattle were driven on the property by hired Indian hands. Mrs. Abbott speaks about the J.H. Edens family, i.e. Mrs. Jukes, Mrs. Henderson, and Mrs. Carr. Mrs. Abbott talks about other details of the Roeder/Roth House, i.e. the gardner. Howard concludes his interview with Mrs. Abbott. Howard adds more information that wasn't recorded. Howard speaks about the designer of the Roth House. Interview with Mr. & Mrs. Jukes. They all discuss the original name of Marine Drive in Bellingham and Marietta that use to be known as Lummi Road. Howard asks about the Eldridge house. Mrs. Jukes talks about how long Eldridge lived in his house before he died and the house burned down in 1894. Mr. Jukes talks about the forest fire of 1894. Howard asks for a comparison between the Eldridge and Roeder/Roth Houses. Howard asks Mrs. Jukes if she recalls seeing the big salt-water canoes on the ocean.
  - Arthur Granger, 1956 October 12; 1956 November 20 (Reel-to-reel Reel #7)
    Cassette Tape #1: Arthur speaks to his father's religious beliefs and arrival to Lummi Island. Arthur tells of his father's part in the Indian wars. Arthur's family was one of the first white families to live on Lummi Island, settling in 1874. He talks about his family. Arthur speaks to working at Al Kirby's trap at Point Roberts and fishing the Fraser River for Sockeye. Speaks to Frank Wright's fish traps and Carslile Cannery. Talks about volume of fish harvested from the traps. Story of when the S.S. Bellingham ran into Frank Wright's traps. Speaks to Smugglers Cove/Deep Water Bay/Inati Bay, how it got its name. Speaks to various ships that Frank Wright owned and that were operated in the area. Fish traps along Village Point, who owned and operated them. Fish traps around the Islands. Chinese workers at the Carslile Cannery. Other non-European workers at Carslile Cannery. Other cannery operaters in the Whatcom area.
    Cassette Tape #2: Continues to speak on cannery operators. Japanese Cannery operators and workers in Anacortes and Lummi Island. Saw/shingle mills on Lummi Island.(Second Interview with Arthur Granger) Talks about Bill Pollard who lived on Clark Island and smuggled Chinese workers to the canneries in the Whatcom area. Speaks to coal mines in the Sehome area. Speaks to old time settlers on the Islands, Lummi Island, Clark Island, Barnes Island. Speaks to Kelly family. "Smuggler Kelly" who use to smuggle Chinese workers into the area, and was renowed for his cruelty. Recalls Captain Smith who lived on Matia Island. Henry Beard and his fox farm on Matia Island. Smokehouse on Matia Island. Stills and alcohol smuggling on Matia Island. Japanese workers in Maple Bay. Ernie Berry and Carslile Cannery. Wong Tung who operated Carslile Cannery before Ernie Berry. Philopeno workers on Lummi Island. Wages for non-European workers.
    Cassette Tape #3: The year Frank Wright took over the Carslile Cannery. Arthur speaks to working for Frank Wright on the fish traps. Granger recalls the Norweigen workers Wright sought to man the fish traps. Recalls Carslile, the founder of the Carslile Cannery. Recalls working Frank Wright's farm on Lummi Island on a 50/50 basis. [Break in tape where reel was turned]. Continues speaking about the first plane Arthur saw around Lummi Island when he was working Frank Wright's farm. Speaks of sowing and pasturing Frank Wright's fields, until Frank Wright went bankrupt. Speaks to selling the farm produce. Granger Home on the Village Point, and then Point Migley. Speaks to Bill Pollard murdering a man over a game of cards in Point Roberts, and Father Boulet coming to get him out of jail. Howard Buswell tells a story about Bill Pollard and his wife. Arthur continues talking about Bill Pollard. Speaks to permanent residents of Barnes Island, and how Barnes Island was used to breed small fur bearing animals.
    Cassette Tape #4: Buswell interludes to insert Sweeny as the victim of Bill Pollard. Another interview picks up with Arthur talking about an adventure he had with Bill Harnden. Speaks to the start of Carslile Packing Company. Speaks to the post office set up by Frank Wright on Lummi Island. Buswell speaks to meeting and talking to Frank Wright's third wife. (Slight overlap where reel is changed.) Arthur and Howard speak to Frank Wright's first and second wives, and his children with his first wife (with whom he wasn't legally married). Arthur Granger's wife (Genie) speaks to her knowledge of Frank Wright's first wife, and the legality of their union. Speaks to Dickerson, who now lives on Lummi Island Land Company land. Buswell speaks to Frank Wright's ship. Speaks to Maude Wright, Frank Wright's third wife. Genie Granger speaks to Leigh Wright, Frank Wright's second wife.
    Cassette Tape #5: Howard and Arthur speaks to Friend, who helped establish the Post Office on Lummi Island. Buswell lists the first homesteaders on Lummi Island and Arthur recalls them as neighbors. Genie Granger speaks of where she grew up. Arthur tells of the steel ships that once ran aground on Lummi Island. November 20, 1956. Tape is about half full.
  - Arthur Granger, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #7a)
    Cassette Tape #1: Arthur speaks about the first picnic on Lummi Island on July 4 in the 1880s. Buswell asks about the picnic that Frank Wright gave in 1912, for the Indian community, of which very few white people attended. Arthur talks about Captain Jack who ran a large canoe (Chinook canoe as Arthur calls them) over to Lummi Island. Howard speaks of when the Portage was all one piece of land in 1859 according to the survey map. Howard talks about Mahoney Point off Cagey Road, after Frank Mahoney. Speaks to the Allen family, Sam and John Allen, who were of a white father and Indian mother. Genie Granger speaks about Constance Lane, who lives in Sitka, Alaska. Howard talks about August Lane's three daughters. Arthur and Howard recall the Native community speaking Chinook Jargon, and their Native language. Genie recalls the Canadian Indians who would come down and pick apples from their property. Arthur speaks to the Natives being able to navigate the fog on the bay as a contrast to their supposed fear of the mountains because of cougars. Howard recalls when all the Lummi people spoke only their language. Arthur laments that Lummi children of the 1950s do not speak their language, but he has witnessed that they can understand their parents when they speak in Lummi. Genie Granger speaks to meeting with Mrs. John Brown. Both Arthur and Genie attest to the cleanliness of the houses on the reservation. Howard recalls his interview with Mrs. John Brown.
    Cassette Tape #2: Genie recalls John Brown. Arthur Granger talks about working with John Brown cutting boats. Howard interviews William Granger, Arthur's grandson who is in the sixth grade at the school on Lummi Island. Howard interviews Frank Moore, at Arthur Granger's house. Frank speaks of acquiring rice whiskey on Clarks Island. End. (Tape about half full)
  - Bill King, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #8)
    Cassette Tape #1: Bill King to discuss Lummi Island history. He came to the island in 1915. He was a logger before being a ship man. He took job for Lummi Bay Packing Company on the cannery ships. Bill King discusses the Lydia Tompson which was a passenger, freight and mail ship. Bill King talks about the route that his ship would take around the islands, this was in 1902. Bill King then talks about the Clallam, a ship he worked on after the Lydia Tompson. Bill King gives the route of the Clallam from Seattle to Victoria. Bill King speaks of the incident in 1904 where the Clallam ran into weather and struck a dock. Women and children were evacuated from the ship. Bill King's sister was on one of the lifeboats that capsized. Bill King recounts the events on the main ship until it sank.
    Cassette Tape #2: Bill King talks about the salvage from the ship. Bill King on the Alice Gertrude that use to run to Neah Bay. (Tape breaks where reel was changed) Bill King on the aftermath of the Clallam wreck. Bill King on aftermath of the Clallam wreck continues. Bill King on the Nooksack Cannery and the Chinese workers. Bill King on the employment of Non-European workers in the canneries on the Rosario Straits Islands. Bill King on the Indian workers in the canneries. Bill King on the Native population clamming and fishing in the islands. Bill King on the gathering in 1913 giving by Frank Wright for the Lummi and other Indians. Bill King on Friend who first owned the Carslile Cannery and the Carslile traps. Bill King on how Frank Wright acquired the Carslile Cannery. Bill King on how Frank Wright lost his fortune.
    Cassette Tape #3: Bill King on Frank Wright continues. Howard Buswell reviews Bill King's interview on Oct 17, 1956. January 15, 1964, Howard Buswell documents the passing of Bill King. (Tape ends about half way through)
  - Chris Siegel, 1956 November 7 (Reel-to-reel Reel #9)
    Cassette Tape #1: (Howard Buswell is a difficult to hear, Chris Siegel is very clear) Siegel on shingle weaver's trousers. Siegel on the location of shingle mills that he can recall in Marietta and Ferndale. Siegel on early trading at Marietta in 1883-1890. Siegel on the Morrison's who built a mill in Ferndale and Marietta. Siegel recalls the Log Jam on the Nooksack River. Siegel speculates on the cause of the Log Jam in 1893. Siegel recalls the pilings in Lummi Bay, and fishing for flounders with the Allen boys. Siegel on the flood of the Nooksack, and the change of the original channel of the Nooksack in 1893. Siegel on threshing with the Wynn brothers on the Lummi reservation. Siegel recalls the distribution of people on the Lummi reservation. Siegel speaks on the differences between the younger generation of Lummis who attended Tulalip Indian Boarding School and the older generation that did not attend boarding school. Siegel on Rogers' shingle mill in Marietta. Siegel on the Taylor Slough. Siegel speaks on coming to Marietta in 1883 on the old Washington ship. Speaks to his canoe travels up the Nooksack River with Indian guides. Howard Buswell recounts Siegel's trip from Seattle to Ferndale. Siegel recalls the terrain (i.e. who lived where) from the east side of the present day Lummi reservation to the Ferndale area. Siegel on pheasant and duck hunting.
    Cassette Tape #2: Siegel continues on duck hunting on Tennant Lake. Siegel tells a story about a giant cedar tree below the Bennent's place where the body of a drowned boy was found by local seer Chris Seaman. Siegel tells of other things Seaman found. Howard recalls Chris Seaman, and his salon. Siegel recalls George Swiloose, who was arrested for murder, and escaped. He was brought back and tried and acquitted. Siegel elaborates on the details of the trial of George Swiloose. Oct. 29, 1956. Reel is turned. Siegel talks about the Allen family. Siegel talks about trading at MacDonald's in Marietta. Siegel on the route he took through the homesteads from Laurel to Marietta. Siegel resumes talking about the Allen family. Howard Buswell recalls the Northwest Road when it was undeveloped. Siegel describes the Allen family as "trying to be white" although they had Indian blood in them.
    Cassette Tape #3: Siegel speaks of Mrs. Allen, who was a Lummi women. Siegel talks about the flooding of the Skagit. Howard asks about steam boats traveling as far up the river as Everson. Siegel recalls the interpreters at the Swiloose trial, who interpreted the testimony of non-English speaking Native Americans. Howard asks about Captain Siegel. (Tape breaks where reel was changed). Siegel speaks of the fire of 1894 that took out Fort Bellingham and North Bellingham and followed Squalicum Creek to Marietta. Siegel speaks of the homestead process, preemption claims. Howard Buswell speaks of his knowledge of snag boats making up the Nooksack past Everson. Howard Buswell speaks of the Slater Slough. Howard Buswell asks about MacDonald and his ocean-going canoe. Siegel speaks of his timber working experience. Howard Buswell recalls the timber mills in Ferndale.
  - Philip Clark, Mary Brown and Alfred Cayou, 1956 November 15 (Reel-to-reel Reel #10)
    Cassette Tape #1: Howard asks about the horse races on the tideflats that the Lummis use to have, near the recent smokehouse, or where the old church was located. Philip Clark and Mary Brown talk about the races and picnic the Lummis use to have on the reservation. Howard asks where Steve's house orginated. Mary answers that it was a school house/church where she went to school. Mary talks about the store on the corner in Fort Bellingham, i.e. who use to own it. Phil recalls who built the store on the corner, and recalls the owners following. Mary talks about Haggen's Bakery. Howard recalls who lived in Fort Bellingham, around the store and bakery, when he first came the area in 1906. Howard talks about Hainey's house, and the Bates' family. Howard asks about Frank Kennedy moving his house from one side of the river the other. Mary speculates on the date that Frank Kennedy moved his house, Phil also discusses it. Phil speaks of pile driving on the slough network around Marietta. Phil discusses the river course in the early 1900s. Phil speaks about Henry Slater when he was first county commissioner, and his inability to solve the flooding problem with the Nooksack River. Mary talks about the Haggen brothers. Howard asks about settlers of the 1880s: Phil talks about Captain Mathews, and Dave Ladimore. Mary and Phil speak about Pete Hammer. Howard, Mary and Phil discuss the ice house in Marietta.
    Cassette Tape #2: Howard speaks about Pete Hammer selling ice in Whatcom. Howard asks about Fred Lane of Lummi Island who eventually bought land in Marietta. Phil talks about McGuiness and Fred Lane. Howard asks about August and Charley Lane who had land on the reservation on Point Francis. Phil talks about the naming of Lane Spit. Howard talks about Whitney Wier, who was coroner in 1925. Alfred talks about fishing in the big salt-water canoes. Alfred talks about the amount of sockeye that one canoe could hold. Phil and Alfred talk about salmon fishing by using kelp beds out of the salt-water canoes. You cut a hole through the kelp about 30 feet wide and then place your net in the hole in the kelp to disguise it. This is described as "Indian reef netting." Alfred talks about using cedar ropes made out of cedar limbs and bark to fashion a traditional reef-net. Phil and Alfred talk about cedar mats and baskets made out of cedar roots. Phil speaks to seeing the local Indians boil potatoes in a basket. Alfred speaks to cooking foods in a basket using hot rocks to heat the water. Howard asks Alfred about baking salmon on poles laid across the fire. Alfred elaborates on this form of cooking. Howard talks about the pictures he has of Kanaki Bay, which pictures canoes up on boom sticks. Alfred speaks of fishing on Kanaki Bay. Alfred speaks about his father and sister Josephine who married Sam Cagey. Alfred talks about his closest living relatives, Henry Cayou in West Sound, another sister Josephine in Olympia. Howard concludes by expressing regrets about cutting off the end of the interview. [The rest of the reel sounds like a recording of a radio program.]
  - Knute Aker and Mrs. Aker, undated (Reel-to-reel Reel #11)